Register of the Robert Daniel Murphy papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert D. Murphy papers
1913-1978
78060
Hoover Institution Archives
177 manuscript boxes, 17 oversize boxes, 3 card file boxes, 67 envelopes, 5 phonotape reels (80.0 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, dispatches, speeches and writings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Allied diplomacy during World War II (especially preparatory to the invasion of French North Africa), wartime and postwar diplomatic conferences, administration of occupied Germany, postwar American foreign relations, and international business enterprises. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Murphy, Robert D. (Robert Daniel), 1894-1978
Access
The collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
1894, October 28 Born, Milwaukee, Wisconsin
1917-1919 Clerk, American Legation, Bern, Switzerland
1920 LL.B., George Washington University
1921 Married, Mildred Taylor Vice Consul, Zurich, Switzerland
1921-1925 Vice Consul, Munich, Germany
1925 Consul, Seville, Spain
1928 LL.M., George Washington University
1926-1930 Department of State, Washington, D.C.
1930-1940 Consul, Paris, France
1940 Charge d'affaires, Vichy, France
1940-1942 Presidential envoy to French North Africa
1941 Concluded economic accord with General Maxime Weygand
1942 Effected preparations for Allied landings in North Africa
1942-1944 Chief Civil Affairs Officer and Political Adviser on Staff of Supreme Commander Co-chairman, North African Economic Board
1942-1943 Member, Advisory Council, Allied Control Commission for Italy
1944-1949 U.S. Political Adviser, Germany
1949 Director, Office for Germany and Austria, Department of State
1949-1952 Ambassador to Belgium
1952-1953 Ambassador to Japan
1953 Assistant Secretary of State for United Nations Affairs
1953-1959 Deputy Under Secretary of State
1959 Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs Retirement from government service
1960-1978 Successively President, Chairman of the Board, and Honorary Chairman of the Board, Corning Glass Works, Corning Glass International
1964 Author, Diplomat Among Warriors
1968-1969 Member, Presidential Transition Committee
1973-1975 Member, Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy
1969-1976 Member (Chairman, 1976), Intelligence Oversight Board Member, President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board
1978, January 9 Died, Washington, D.C.
Foreword
From humble beginnings, Robert D. Murphy became one of America's leading diplomats and statesmen. In a distinguished public service career that lasted almost sixty years, Ambassador Murphy had the good fortune to serve in interesting places at interesting times. He also had the good judgment to preserve the records of his extraordinary experiences, records that now constitute the Robert D. Murphy Collection at the Hoover Institution Archives.
One of Murphy's first diplomatic posts, in the early 1920s, was Vice Consul in Munich, where he reported to Washington on the rise of national socialism and where he lived across the street from the Nazi leader, Adolf Hitler. Throughout the 1930s, he served as Consul in Paris. When German troops entered the city in June 1940, Murphy met with the German commanding general in order to safeguard American and French interests. Later that year, he was appointed Charge d'Affaires at Vichy.
Shortly thereafter, President Franklin Roosevelt chose Murphy to be his special envoy to French North Africa. Roosevelt, realizing the vital role that French North Africa could play in the war, wanted a trusted personal representative to investigate conditions and report back directly to him. Robert Murphy proved the wisdom of Roosevelt's choice when his careful negotiations laid the groundwork for the successful Allied invasion of North Africa in 1942. The Murphy Papers for this period include communications with President Roosevelt and other wartime leaders, memoranda from American Ambassador to Vichy William Leahy, military and secret service (Office of Strategic Services) reports of Allied operations, as well as the diplomatic records of the wartime conferences of Allied leaders at Casablanca and Cairo.
Murphy continued his service in Africa as political adviser under General Dwight D. Eisenhower until 1944, when he was sent to Italy as American Ambassador on the Advisory Council to the Allied Control Commission. In his new post, he participated in the signing of the Italian armistice. Murphy's intimate involvement with the Allied high command laid the basis for his subsequent memoirs, Diplomat Among Warriors (1964).
His next assignment took him to Germany as a member of the Office of Military Government, which was set up to administer postwar reconstruction. During these years, he also served on American delegations to the Councils of Foreign Ministers in Moscow, London, and Paris, and to the Tri-Partite Talks. The records of these conferences, including the most secret negotiations, reports, memoranda and correspondence are part of the Murphy Papers. There are as well rare captured German documents, including transcripts of wartime conferences of Hitler with his top military commanders.
In 1949, Robert Murphy was appointed United States Ambassador to Belgium and, in 1952, the first American postwar Ambassador to Japan. During his tenure in Tokyo, he also acted as Political Adviser to the United Nations Command in connection with the negotiations on the Korean War armistice. From 1953 to 1959, his assignment to the Department of State involved him in negotiations with leaders in many parts of the world: Tito in Yugoslavia, Saeb Salam in Lebanon, Bourguiba in Tunisia and King Hussein in Jordan. Shortly before he retired from government service in 1959, he served as Under Secretary of State. Records of Murphy's many important assignments during these years appear in his papers.
After his retirement, Murphy began a new career as an executive with Corning Glass International where he successfully combined his new duties with his role as elder statesman. He served on the Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board during the Kennedy, Johnson and Nixon administrations, as well as on the Intelligence Oversight Board and the Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy. Memoranda, reports and internal communications from these many significant assignments appear in the Murphy papers.
The vast correspondence Murphy carried on throughout his life is of equal importance to historians. There are letters to and from a wide assortment of important people: world leaders Andrei Vyshinsky, Harold Macmillan and Konrad Adenauer; Presidents Franklin Roosevelt, Harry Truman and Dwight Eisenhower; Secretaries of State James Byrnes, Cordell Hull, Dean Acheson and John Foster Dulles; French military leaders Charles de Gaulle, Maxime Weygand, Henri Giraud and Jean Darlan; movie actors Douglas Fairbanks and Adolphe Menjou, and violinist Yehudi Menuhin.
The register to the Robert D. Murphy Collection is composed of four parts. A Biographical Note indicates important dates in the course of Murphy's career. The overall structure of the collection is outlined in the Series Description, which explains its major divisions. The Container List describes in detail the materials within each series. An Index (available in the paper copy only) provides a single alphabetical listing of all access points in the register with page references.
A few items in the papers retain national security classifications. Until such time as they can be declassified, they have been withdrawn from the collection and their withdrawal is so noted in the register.
The Robert D. Murphy Papers, a gift to the Hoover Institution Archives by his daughters, Rosemary Murphy and Mildred Pond, in 1978, are open to the public without charge. The Archives Reading Room is open on weekdays from 8:15 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. For further information, please contact Hoover Institution Archives, Stanford University, Stanford, California, 94305.
I am especially pleased to acknowledge the generous financial support of the Corning Glass Works Foundation, Corning, New York, without which the preparation and publication of this guide would not have been possible.
--Charles G. Palm
--Associate Director, Hoover Institution
--1989
Note: In 2007, additional incremental materials added to the Robert D. Murphy Collection were organized. Please see the description on Incremental Materials below the description of the original accession.
Scope and Content Note, Incremental Materials
The incremental material to the Robert Murphy Papers, acquired in 2003, consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, dispatches, speeches and writings, printed matter, photographs, and scrapbooks, relating to Allied diplomacy during World War II, wartime and postwar diplomatic conferences, administration of occupied Germany, postwar American foreign relations, and international business enterprises. The collection originates from Robert Murphy's official assignments with the State Department, his extensive professional travels, and his involvement with private organizations dedicated to promote peace, freedom, and friendship between people from different political and religious backgrounds.
The bulk of the materials document Robert Murphy's tenure as presidential envoy to North Africa; political adviser, Office of Military Government, United States; adviser for Germany and Austria; ambassador to Japan and Belgium; assistant secretary of state for United Nations affairs; deputy under secretary of state; and under secretary of state for political affairs, and are documented in several series tied to periods of his career. They reflect his diplomatic skills and record his efforts to protect American interests. The later part of Robert Murphy's career, as recorded in Later Years, was a combination of activities in both the business and political arena, highlighted by his participation in the Presidential Transition Committee, Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy, Intelligence Oversight Board, and President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board.
The numerous awards and certificates documented in the Biographical File, Memorabilia, and Oversize File reflect the high esteem in which both fellow diplomats and political leaders held Robert Murphy. The Photograph series provides a glimpse into his personal life, in addition to portraying him as a diplomat. Scrapbooks and clippings included in the Biographical File offer a review of his life and career and an assessment of his contributions to the field of American foreign policy and international diplomacy.
Arrangement
Materials arranged into ten series: Biographical File I, Speeches and Writings I, Early Career, Presidential Envoy to French North Africa and Political Advisor I, Political Advisor I, Ambassadorships - Department of State I, Later Years I, Oversize File I, Phonotapes, Photographs I.
Incremental Materials arranged into nine series, duplicating the order of the original finding aid: Biographical File II, Speeches and Writings II, Presidential Envoy to French North Africa and Political Advisor II, Political Advisor II, Ambassadorships II, Later Years II, Memorabilia, Oversize File II, Photographs II, and Declassified U.S. government records.
Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters.; Bilderberg Meetings.; Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government.; United States. Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy.; United States. Department of State.; Audiotapes.; Business enterprises--United States.; Diplomats--United States.; France--Foreign relations--United States.; France.; Germany--History--1945-1955.; Germany.; International business enterprises.; Military government.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Economic conditions--1945-; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; United States--Foreign relations--1953-1961.; United States--Foreign relations--France.; United States--Foreign relations.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Africa, North.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File I, 1913-1971
  Scope and Contents note
  This file contains personal materials, including awards, citations, appointment books, clippings, honorary degrees and souvenirs; arranged by physical form.
  - Appointment books, schedules
    - 1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - September, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
    - 1956, October -1958, July (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
    - 1958, August-1959 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Awards (Folder 3-4)
  - Biographical data (Folder 5)
  - Career records. Assignment records, promotion notices, travel orders, organization charts, and correspondence related to the career of Robert Murphy
    - 1913-1919 (Folder 6)
    - 1920 (Folder 7)
    - 1921 (Folder 8)
    - 1922 (Folder 9)
    - 1923 (Folder 10)
    - 1924 (Folder 11)
    - 1925 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - 1926 (Folder 3)
    - 1927 (Folder 4)
    - 1928 (Folder 5)
    - 1929 (Folder 6)
    - 1930 (Folder 7)
    - 1931 (Folder 8)
    - 1932 (Folder 9)
    - 1933 (Folder 10)
    - 1934 (Folder 11)
    - 1935 (Folder 12)
    - 1936 (Folder 13)
    - 1937 (Folder 14)
    - 1938 (Folder 15)
    - 1939 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1940 (Folder 2)
    - 1941 (Folder 3)
    - 1942 (Folder 4)
    - 1943 (Folder 5)
    - 1944 (Folder 6)
    - 1945 (Folder 7)
    - 1946 (Folder 8)
    - 1947 (Folder 9)
    - 1948 (Folder 10)
    - 1949 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - 1950 (Folder 3)
    - 1951 (Folder 4-5)
    - 1952 (Folder 6-8)
    - 1953 (Folder 9)
    - 1954 (Folder 10)
    - 1960 (Folder 11)
    - 1961-1967 (Folder 12)
  - Clippings about Robert D. Murphy
    - 1920 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1925 (Folder 2)
    - 1926 (Folder 3)
    - 1930-1931 (Folder 4)
    - 1939 (Folder 5)
    - 1941 (Folder 6)
    - 1942 (Folder 7)
    - 1943 (Folder 8)
    - 1944 (Folder 9)
    - 1945 (Folder 10)
    - 1946 (Folder 11)
    - 1948 (Folder 12)
    - 1949 (Folder 13-17)
    - 1950 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1952 (Folder 2)
    - 1954 (Folder 3)
    - 1956 (Folder 4)
    - 1957 (Folder 5)
    - 1958 (Folder 6-11)
    - 1958 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - 1959 (Folder 4)
    - 1960 (Folder 5)
    - 1961 (Folder 6)
    - 1962 (Folder 7-8)
    - 1963 (Folder 9)
    - 1964 (Folder 10)
    - 1965 (Folder 11)
    - 1966 (Folder 12)
    - 1967 (Folder 13)
    - 1968 (Folder 14)
    - 1970 (Folder 15)
    - 1971 (Folder 16)
  - Education. Papers related to Robert Murphy's candidacy for a Master of Laws Degree from George Washington University, 1927-1928 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Family clippings (Folder 3)
  - Coat of arms (Folder 4)
  - Family memorabilia (Folder 5)
  - Guest lists (Folder 6-7)
  - Health. Physical examination records (Folder 8)
  - Honorary degrees (Folder 9-10)
  - Household expenses, personal effects, employees (Folder 11-12)
  - Household expenses, etc. (Box 14, Folder 1-10)
  - Household expenses, etc. (Box 15, Folder 1-9)
  - Household expenses, etc. (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Identity cards (Folder 3)
  - Interview. List of questions for Robert Murphy from Grand Hebdomadaire Illustre, July, 1943 (Folder 4)
  - Invitations, calling cards, laissez passers (Folder 5)
  - Miscellany (Folder 6-9)
  - Miscellany (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Souvenirs. Programs, brochures, guest lists (Folder 2-8)
  - Telephone directories (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
  - Travel orders (Folder 3-5)
  - Trip notes, February, 1941 (Folder 6)
- Speeches and Writings I, 1937-1977
  Handwritten, typewritten, and printed copies of speeches and writings by Robert Murphy with related notes and research materials; arranged chronologically.
  - Notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - "The Utility of a Permanent and Trained Foreign Service", Handwritten draft, undated (Folder 8)
  - "Income Tax Returns", The American Foreign Service Journal, l printed copy, September, 1937 (Folder 9)
  - Remarks at the University Club of Paris, Correspondence, 3 carbon copies, May 2, 1939 (Folder 10)
  - Remarks at the American Club of Paris, 3 carbon copies, July 20, 1939 (Folder 11)
  - Research materials, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Research materials, 1944-1945 (Folder 2-3)
  - Notes for public remarks, circa 1944 (Folder 4)
  - Remarks on the Mediterranean Theater, Council of Foreign Relations, New York, Typescript copy, January 27, 1944 (Folder 5)
  - Notes on remarks made to French Military Government students, Paris, Typescript copy in French, December 15, 1944 (Folder 6)
  - "The American Military Policy Towards Germany", Correspondence, typescript, carbon copies, draft, December 16, 1944 (Folder 7)
  - Remarks to French Military Government officers, Paris, Typescript copy in French, February 7, 1945 (Folder 8)
  - Remarks on Political Affairs, Paris, Outline, typescript copy, February 14, 1945 (Folder 9)
  - "Germany and Democracy", Military Government Conference, Frankfurt, Program, typescript copy, August 17, 1945 (Folder 10)
  - Remarks to American correspondents, Typescript copy, December 11, 1945 (Folder 11)
  - Research materials, 1946 (Folder 12-15)
  - "Foreign Policy", written for Berlin Post, Correspondence, carbon copy, February 4, 1946 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Remarks, Bremerhaven, Carbon copy, May 11, 1946 (Folder 2)
  - Remarks on the German Occupation, Typescript copy, August 21, 1946 (Folder 3)
  - Remarks on U.S. Policy, Carbon copy, October 24, 1946 (Folder 4)
  - Research materials, 1947 (Folder 5)
  - Remarks at dedication of synagogue, Munich, Draft, May 20, 1947 (Folder 6)
  - Notes for Berlin seminar, 2 carbon copies, May 28, 1947 (Folder 7)
  - Commencement address, Roberts High School, Berlin, Notes, typescript and carbon copies, July 11, 1947 (Folder 8)
  - Remarks to Syracuse University alumni, Berlin, Outline, August 17, 1947 (Folder 9)
  - "Murphy Stresses Importance of Spiritual Values in Reconstruction of Germany", interview, Printed copy, December 15, 1947 (Folder 10)
  - Research materials, 1948 (Folder 11-12)
  - "Foreign Policy", Notes, outline, circa 1948 (Folder 13)
  - Remarks on Germany, Typescript copy, circa 1948 (Folder 14)
  - Remarks on postwar Germany, Typescript copy, circa 1948 (Folder 15)
  - Remarks at commencement, institution unknown, Handwritten copy, circa 1948 (Folder 16)
  - "The United States Views Germany's Democratization", Carbon copy, circa 1948 (Folder 17)
  - Remarks to American Women's Club, Berlin, Typescript copy, January 6, 1948 (Folder 18)
  - Remarks on Germany, Louisville, Kentucky, Typescript copy, February 10, 1948 (Folder 19)
  - "The Ruhr and Security", Carbon copy, May 20, 1948 (Folder 20)
  - Commencement address, Roberts High School, Berlin, Carbon copy, June 15, 1948 (Folder 21)
  - Notes, drafts, 1949 (Folder 22)
  - Research materials, 1949 (Folder 23)
  - Remarks on the German problem, National Advertising Council, Washington, D.C., 4 carbon copies, February 9, 1949 (Folder 24)
  - Remarks on Germany delivered by Robert Murphy on behalf of the Secretary of State, Washington, D.C., Typescript copy, March 30, 1949 (Folder 25)
  - "The Role of the Political Adviser to the Military Governor", National War College, Washington, D.C., Printed copy, carbon copy, October 17, 1949 (Folder 26)
  - Research materials, 1950 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Remarks, Carbon copy, January 13, 1950 (Folder 3)
  - Remarks at the Belgian-American Association luncheon, Brussels, 4 typescript copies (2 in English, 2 in French), January 25, 1950 (Folder 4)
  - Remarks at a reception for the mayor and aldermen, Antwerp, 2 typescript copies (1 in French, 1 in English), January 27, 1950 (Folder 5)
  - Remarks at the Cercle Industrielle et Commerciale, Typescript, February 9, 1950 (Folder 6)
  - Remarks, Military Order of Foreign Wars, 2 carbon copies, February 14, 1950 (Folder 7)
  - Remarks, Brussels Chamber of Commerce, 4 typescript copies (2 in English, 2 in French), February 20, 1950 (Folder 8)
  - Remarks, George Washington's Birthday dinner, Typescript, carbon copy, February 25, 1950 (Folder 9)
  - Remarks, Cercle Gaulois, Brussels, 2 typescript copies (1 in French, 1 in English), memorandum, March 15, 1950 (Folder 10)
  - Remarks, American-Belgian Association, 2 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French), March 24, 1950 (Folder 11)
  - Remarks, American Club of Paris, 2 typescript copies, March 30, 1950 (Folder 12)
  - Remarks at Zeebrugge, 2 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French), May 12, 1950 (Folder 13)
  - Remarks, Carbon copy, May 23, 1950 (Folder 14)
  - Remarks, Memorial Day, 3 typescript copies (2 in English, 1 in French), May 30, 1950 (Folder 15)
  - Remarks, Jesus College, Oxford, 2 typescript copies, July 2, 1950 (Folder 16)
  - Remarks, Bastogne Memorial, 4 typescript copies (2 in French, 2 in English), July 16, 1950 (Folder 17)
  - Remarks, Foire de Gand (Ghent Fair), 2 drafts, 5 typescript copies (2 in English, 2 in French, 1 in Dutch), September 18, 1950 (Folder 18)
  - Remarks, Polytechnic Institute, Mons, and the Belgian-American Association, 4 typescripts (2 in French, 2 in English), November 28, 1950 (Folder 19)
  - Remarks, Cercle Mars et Mercure, 3 typescript copies (2 in French, 1 in English), carbon copy, December 7, 1950 (Folder 20)
  - Notes, drafts, 1951 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Research materials, 1951 (Folder 2-4)
  - Remarks, American Chamber of Commerce, Typescript, carbon copy, January 16, 1951 (Folder 5)
  - Remarks, American Club luncheon. 2 typescript copies, 2 press releases (Folder 6)
  - Remarks, Royal Automobile Club, 2 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French), February 12, 1951 (Folder 7)
  - Remarks, University of Louvain, 2 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French), February 13, 1951 (Folder 8)
  - Remarks, George Washington's Birthday Dinner, 2 typescript copies (1 in French, 1 in English), February 23, 1951 (Folder 9)
  - Remarks, Flemish Economic Association, 3 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French, 1 in Flemish), April 16, 1951 (Folder 10)
  - Remarks, Third Liege International Fair, 2 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French), April 23, 1951 (Folder 11)
  - Remarks, Brussels Fair, 2 typescript copies (1 in French, 1 in English), April 27, 1951 (Folder 12)
  - Remarks, Belgian-American Association, 2 typescript copies (1 in French, 1 in English), May 28, 1951 (Folder 13)
  - Remarks, Waereghem, 2 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French), June 3, 1951 (Folder 14)
  - Remarks, Ghent Fair, 3 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French, 1 in Flemish), September 18, 1951 (Folder 15)
  - Remarks, American Club of Brussels, 3 typescript copies (1 in English, 1 in French, 1 in Flemish), September 20, 1951 (Folder 16)
  - Remarks, Virginia Women's Forum, Richmond, Virginia, 4 typescript copies (2 in French, 2 in English), November 8, 1951 (Folder 17)
  - "The United States and West European Unity", National Foreign Trade Council, New York, Typescript, draft, December 7, 1951 (Folder 18)
  - Research materials, 1952 (Box 23, Folder 1)